A Guide to the Edward L. Stone/Borderland Coal Company Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Edward L. Stone/Borderland Coal Company Papers 1895-1937
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
382
This collection consists of approximately 500,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Stored off-site. Users must request boxes 48 hours in advance of desired use. Neither drop-in nor next-day requests can be fulfilled. For additional information, contact Special Collections.
Acquisition Information
Before his death in 1938, the University of Virginia Library had been negotiating with Edward L. Stone for the purchase of his library. Mr. Stone had donated a number of fine books, and some manuscripts, to the University of Virginia Library, and its staff knew the value of his fine private library. The tentative purchase price settled upon was low principally because Mr. Stone wished his library to remain intact. Unfortunately, Mr. Stone died before negotiations were complete, but the Library concluded the sale with his heirs in August 1938. As a result of this purchase, the Stone Printing and Manufacturing Company of Roanoke presented to the Library the files of correspondence and other papers both of Mr. Stone's extensive business interests and of his personal affairs. The collection consisted of 207 letter boxes and twenty-five "large packing cases" when it arrived at the Library on August 11, 1939.
Biographical/Historical Information
Biography of Edward L. Stone
Edward Lee Stone was born on September 15, 1864, in Liberty (now Bedford) Virginia, the son of John Harmon Stone and Mary Witt Stone. He was reared in very modest circumstances, and received no more than an elementary school education, yet he became one of the wealthiest and most prominent citizens in the state of Virginia.
Edward Stone's career in the printing business is typical of the fabled American dream. At ten years of age, having recently lost his father, Stone was in the boys' playground of his school. J. R. Guy, the editor of the Bedford Sentinel newspaper, came to the playground looking for William Fellers, Stone's cousin. When Stone asked Mr. Guy what he wanted with William, Guy replied "I want him to carry the papers. Stone said, "I'll carry 'em' for you." After being a delivery boy for the Sentinel, Stone learned to set type and worked evenings after school for five cents an evening; twenty-five cents on Saturday. Less than a year later, economics necessitated that he quit school to pursue his job full time. Stone learned his lessons well, and showed enthusiasm in every phase of his work. Young Stone worked alongside a window, and enjoyed nothing better than to jump out into the street and scrap with some passing youngster, returning to his duties after the fun was over.
Stone was given more and more duties which he performed to this employer's total satisfaction. At the age of sixteen, for some now-inexplicable reason, Stone left the newspaper business to work for a mercantile establishment, He soon grew bored, however, and returned to printer's ink. This time he worked for the Democrat, a weekly newspaper in Buchanan, Virginia, then a thriving town at the intersection of the James River and the Kanawha Canal.
Once, at the age of sixteen, Stone was entrusted with getting out an entire edition of the paper by himself. The editor was in court and many workmen were out sick. Stone and an assistant set type at breakneck speed beginning at 7:15 A.M. and had the entire seven-column paper completed by noon --an amazing feat. Stone was out playing ball by 2 P.M. and earned a $5.00 bonus from his boss, editor William J. Boyd. In 1882, Boyd informed Stone that he was going to open a printing office in Roanoke, Virginia, then a small town. Boyd wanted Stone to be manager, and on July 20th, 1882, both men arrived in Roanoke. A place could not be found for the new enterprise however, and both returned to Buchanan. Stone became disillusioned with the small scope of opportunities Buchanan provided, and, with an ambition to "become somebody" in the printing business, set out for Lynchburg. Landing in Lynchburg in January 1883 he applied for work on the News and, after a few days, secured a position as compositor. Here he remained until March, achieving considerable reputation as a fast compositor, yet not satisfied. Stone really longed for a position in the printing business. John P. Bell offered Stone a minor position in a branch office he had planned to open in Roanoke. The position was, in most respects, inferior to the one he had already held, but Stone gladly took it. He worked hard, and showed superior business ability which impressed Mr. Bell so much that when the manager of the business died in 1885 his position was offered to Stone. The position was not offered without some misgivings because of Stone's youth (he was only twenty-one) and his lack of business experience. Stone, however, did such a good job as manager that Bell realized that he had made the right choice. Stone eventually gained control of the business and became president of the company.
His position was secure enough that in 1890, he married Miss Minnie Fishburn, daughter of J. A. Fishburn, a prominent business man of Roanoke. The couple had one child, Mary Katherine Stone.
Edward Stone's printing business grew in size and wealth. By 1920 it was acknowledged by many to be the best-equipped printing corporation in the south, and one of the largest as well. He had many other business interests. He was president of the Borderland Coal Corporation, president of the Virginia Bridge and Iron Company, vice president and later president of the Walker Foundry and Machine Company, chairman of the First National Exchange Bank, and president of his primary business and "first love," the Stone Printing and Manufacturing Company.
In March 1896 Stone was presented with a petition signed by fourteen Roanoke business men requesting that he run for mayor. Stone was very tempted, but a law stating that no one in Roanoke public office would be permitted to do business with the city stopped him. Stone felt that not being able to do business with the city would be unfair to his stockholders. Stone, a civic-minded individual, was chairman of the Roanoke Community Fund in 1924, and of the City Planning and Zoning Commission. He was also chairman of the war bond committee during the First World War, and belonged to many societies and organizations, including the American Institute of Graphic Arts, the Florida State Historical Society, the Shenandoah Club of Roanoke, the Country Club of Roanoke, the Roanoke Gun Club, the Roanoke German Club, the Virginia Historical Society (life member), the Better Printing Committee of the United Typothetae of America, the Roanoke Rotary Club, the International Benjamin Franklin Society of New York, and the board of trustees of the Committee to Assist the Blind.
Edward Stone was also an extremely charitable man. He gave large sums of money to the Roanoke Hospital and the Roanoke Relief Fund, helped endow Roanoke College, gave heavily to the Boy Scouts and the War Relief Clearing House, and donated money to the Coal Miner's Relief Fund--even though it was those very coal miners who were striking in Stone's coal mines. He believed, however, that the miners' children should not have to suffer for their parents' stand. The Stones also gave money to support French children who had been left fatherless as a result of the war. Stone, a Presbyterian, donated $100.00 to the Jewish Relief Fund in 1917 to aid the starving Jews in Russia displaced by the war, and also sent funds to the Tuskeegee Institute.
Edward Stone's principal hobby was book collecting, and his library was appraised at $50,000.00 in 1939. Among his treasured pieces was a page from the original Gutenberg Bible. Stone's library was considered to be the largest and best-equipped privately-owned library in the state of Virginia.
Stone's income fluctuated through the years. In 1917 and 1918, partly through stock sales, Stone declared an income of $129,383.39 and $91,483.00 respectively, but 1926 was considered an average year, and he declared an income of $57,500.00.
Although Stone was a humanitarian and philanthropist, he believed in keeping total control of his business and watched his employees closely. He did not strongly oppose unionization in his printing shop, but fully opposed unionization in his coal mines, even using scabs to break strikes.
Stone suffered financial reversals during the Great Depression but he reorganized his holdings to prevent a great loss, and he weathered the Depression better than most businessmen. His health had begun to fail by 1929, and by 1934 he was virtually bedridden. Finally, after a protracted illness, Edward L. Stone died on June 3, 1938, at the age of seventy-four.
A History of the Borderland Coal Company
The Borderland Coal Company derived its name from its dual location in Mingo County, West Virginia, and Pike County, Kentucky, an area bordered by the Tug Fork of the Big Sandy River. The mines proper were located in Kentucky, and the coal washers and other processing equipment were located in West Virginia. The company operated from 1903 to 1934. While the Borderland Coal Company was incorporated in 1903, the first batch of coal was not shipped until September 1, 1904. In that year J. S. Tipton, formerly the majority stockholder, resigned his post as general manager of Borderland Coal and sold most of his stock to Edward L. Stone. At that time Stone was president of the Young Men's Investment Club which owned a large number of shares in the Borderland Coal Company, and thus, Stone controlled the club's activities.
The Borderland Coal Company initially owned approximately 1,000 acres of coal land. The company mined bituminous or soft coal, and sold slack coal, used by railroads and industrial concerns, egg coal, used in private furnaces, and nut coal, the highest quality of bituminous coal, used in the kitchens of private homes.
The Borderland Coal Company grew through the early 1900's. In 1905, a second plant was opened called simply "Operation #2." The company declared its first stock dividend in November 1907, and began the construction of an electric plant, cableway, conveyor, and tipple at a cost of $27,950.00. In 1908 a new coal washer was installed. By late 1914 the Borderland Company held 3,000 acres of coal lands containing an estimated 20,000,000 tons of coal. The profits of the Borderland Coal Company increased from $1,250.00 in 1904 to $11,243.77 in 1905, to $49,977.21 in 1908, and to $110,532.68 in 1910.
The amount of coal mined increased from 246 railroad carloads in 1904 to 3,781 railroad carloads in 1910, and expansion continued until the outbreak of World War I. The coal paid a regular annual dividend averaging 15-30%. Prior to 1911, the Leckie Coal Company of Cleveland, Ohio, was the exclusive agency for the sale of Borderland Coal. In that year, however, the Borderland Coal Sales Company was formed, with officers of the Borderland Coal Company doubling as officials of the new company.
The town of Borderland, West Virginia, was a company town, with company-owned homes, stores, school, and a church. The rents in the company homes appear to have been within the miners' incomes. The prices in the company stores, however, were exorbitant. In fact, profits for the company store were the second biggest money maker for the company in 1911, totaling $11,811.78. The largest profit maker was coal, which netted $91,741.07, while the sale of powder was ranked third, totaling $3,165.86.
World War I created a great demand and a high prices for coal, and the Borderland Coal Company prospered despite difficulty finding railroad cars to transport its produce. In 1917, the company paid a record 60% dividend. On January 1, 1918, the company re-chartered itself in Virginia, and patented the trademark and the name of the Borderland Coal Company. The new capital stock was valued at nearly $800,000.00. In November 1918 construction began on a new tipple at a cost of $116,000.00. After the First World War, the Borderland Coal Company experienced a decrease in both the demand and the price of coal. The problem of labor and unionization, however, ultimately caused the company's demise.
Borderland Coal Company officials had been concerned over the growth of coal mine unionization long before any major trouble began. As early as 1915, L. E. Armentrout, the corporation's Vice President and General Manager began using "secret service men" to infiltrate the ranks of the miners and report on any union activity. It is not known whether these agents were U.S. government agents or private investigators, but the latter is presumed. One of them reported on March 10, 1915:
I spent the entire day Monday with Emmett and Ed McKee, Gus Cantrell, and Henry McKnight, all white Americans. We played cards in an empty house on the Kentucky side. We had a nice fire and everything was very comfortable. We would play cards until we got tired, then we would stop everything and talk unionism. Gus Cantrell said that he had been talking to the boys for the last year, trying to get them to organize a local of the U.M.W. of A. He said that there was plenty of good, solid union men and that there were also a lot of rotten scabs here. That he got into a conversation with George McCormick, a white man, and McCormick told him that he didn't believe in the union and that he didn't want anything to do with the U.M.W. of A.... I told Cantrell that I would be willing to help organize the local. He said, "Well, the work is picking up now and we will wait until the boys get a good pay day, then we will put this thing through."
Borderland Coal Company successfully resisted unionization in the years before World War I. Wartime regulations prevented strikes and hindered unionization, but after the war many miners felt that it was time to air their grievances. Miners disagreed over specific demands, but most felt that grave inequalities existed in the rates for day workers established by the Bituminous Coal Commission. The miners requested that a conference be held but this request was turned down by the Commission. Dissatisfaction became more pronounced, and during the middle of July 1920 the miners in some of the subdistricts walked out in an unauthorized strike. Shutdowns spread to Indiana and Illinois. President Woodrow Wilson intervened and told the miners that if they returned to work a grievance committee would be formed. The miners returned to work August 10, 1920, and the committee was set up. Management and labor agreed on a wage increase and all was quiet for a while.
West Virginia was in a unique position in that most of the mines in that state were non-union. The Interstate Commerce Commission fixed freight rates with a "differential" low enough that West Virginia coal would not be eliminated by production from other fields closer to their market. When the market for coal was good, the differential also allowed the union coal fields of Indiana, Michigan, and Illinois to pay the union scale of wages and still sell their coal in competition with the product of non-union fields, such as those in West Virginia. When the demand for coal was low and prices receded, however, the differential no longer aided the union fields and they began to experience an adverse effect. These conditions appeared after the First World War, and as a result operators of unionized mines demanded the unionization of the Wast Virginia coal fields. Thus the U.M.W. put pressure on all non-union fields, including those of the Borderland Coal Company. Borderland Coal Company had been fairly quiet about unionization up to this time. On May 5, 1920, however, L. E. Armentrout had issued the following notice:
TO THE PRESENT OR FUTURE EMPLOYEES OF THE BORDERLAND COAL COMPANY
Considerable efforts are being made to organize this field and certain advantages are being held out to some men showing the advisability of belonging to the Union.
This is a free country and this company is not going to dictate to its employees whether they shall or shall not join the Union, but for your information and for the information of your friends, we wish to state positively that no Union man will be employed by this company, and if you find that it is to your interest to join the Union, we would suggest that you arrange to move out and call at the office and we will be glad to settle with you. This will save you as well as the company further trouble, but we sincerely hope that the pleasant relations between the Company and the men will continue, and that each and every one of you will continue in our employ.
Yours very truly,
L. E. Armentrout,
Manager
By late May, 1920 the situation had become acute. Armentrout wrote to James P. Woods, president of the Borderland Coal Company:
The organizers have just about put us out of business at both plants... We have a good many men who have not joined the Union, but these agitators are intimidating them and have them so scared they won't attempt to try to work. I will have a conference with the West Virginia attorneys today to see if I cannot get a temporary injunction, or probably prosecution for these intimidators.
We have three Deputy Sheriffs in Kentucky and expect two more in today. We have both plants pretty well policed at night, but still some of the intimidators slip through the mines and get to some of the men...
Now that the primary is over, we believe that Unionism will die out.... In fact, no Union cards have been issued and for the past two or three days they have not been able to locate the man who has been giving them orders on the stores. Some of them (the fired Union Men) have already remarked that they could not support their families on $7.00 to $8.00 a week, and they hated to go to bed at night when their children were crying for something to eat.
Unionism, however, did not die out. Union "agitators" saw to that no coal could be mined at the Borderland Company's coal fields. In a letter to Stone dated July 6, 1920, Armentrout stated that he was able to get "very little action from the Governor of West Virginia.. .I just finished talking to Governor Morrow's office in Frankfort, Kentucky, and the home guards will likely entrain today. They will likely have machine guns so if that they get in according to promise, we think that conditions will improve very rapidly."
The Borderland Coal Company kept its promise and dispossessed hundreds of its employees. Fired from their jobs and ousted from their homes, they were forced to live in tents. In a union pamphlet entitled "Borderland and Bullets" these men told of the horrible indignities forced on company employees who joined the union. The purpose of the pamphlet was to oppose the re-election of Colonel James P. Woods, president of the Borderland Coal Company, to the U. S. House of Representatives. Woods ran for re-election in the sixth Virginia district claiming that he had been always fair to the working man, and he won.
The situation at Borderland soon deteriorated into violence. A pamphlet dated "winter, 1920" and entitled Hell with the Lid Off in Mingo County, West Virginia, gives an account of drunken company guards wounding a number of workers by firing into their tents. On May 12, 1920, Edward Stone, chairman of the board of the Borderland Coal Company, had examined an advertisement for the Thompson sub-machine gun but had decided that "the gun is not sufficient for our needs at the mine." On May 16 Governor John J. Cornwell of West Virginia sent a telegram to the War Department in Washington requesting that Federal troops be sent to the Tug River District, where Borderland Coal Company was located. There had been fighting in the Tug River District for nearly four days. Secretary of War John Weeks, basing his decision on reports from one of his staff officers who had visited the area, decided that federal troops were not needed. Four days later Governor Cornwell declared martial law in West Virginia. Militiamen from both Kentucky and West Virginia were involved in the fighting.
In the summer of 1921 the U. M. W. began its famous "summer march" which precipitated guerilla warfare between the pro-union and anti-union forces. On June 29, Governor Cornwell ordered the citizens of West Virginia to take up arms and defend themselves against the pro-unionists. The papers of the Borderland Coal Company include lists of casualties written on scrap paper, such as "Stone Mountain, 5 Baldwin men and 4 citizens killed (one the mayor), 2 Feltz Bros. killed, 2 military companies there, 2 on the way." In April 1922 the coal miners' grievances came to a head and they struck. They demanded a continuation of the system of bargaining and contract, including the "checkoff," which is a list devised to check on payment of union dues. In addition to demanding stable wage rates, the miners demanded a six-hour day and a five-day week. These increased hours would mean steady employment, one of the miners' main goals.
The strike apparently took some pressure off the Borderland Coal Company because after 1922 there is little or nothing in the collection regarding unionization. Company officials had managed to avoid unionization of their mines but had caused the company much damage in the process. Bitter feelings prevailed after the strike. A letter from L. E. Armentrout to the Borderland Coal Company dated 1923 states:
Gentlemen,
My attention has just been called to the enclosed blotter bearing the union label. It has been the policy of this company for several years, in fact, ever since we have been in business, not to recognize any Union whatever. We spent, or lost, something like $300,000.00 fighting the United Mine Workers here in 1920 and 1921, and also have some injunctions against them.
For your information, please do not place any more printing with any Union shop, and if you have any more of these blotters, tear them up or dispose of them otherwise as it is inconsistent with our policy, and we positively will not stand for it.
While much of the collection regards labor struggles, there is little material regarding immigrant labor although 40% of the workers were immigrants. West Virginia was a sparsely populated state at this time, and immigrants were needed to supplement the labor in their mines. The first constitution of the state provided for the appointment of an immigration officer whose duties were to advertise the attractions of West Virginia throughout Europe and make arrangements with industries to supply transportation for foreign workmen. Of the 80,877 workers employed in the West Virginia coal mines in 1915, 49,753 were American-born (37,918 white and 11,835 black) and 31,124 were foreign-born. Italians made up the largest percentage of the immigrant labor force, about one third of all foreigners employed in the mines while Hungarians comprised the second-most prevalent nationality, approximately one-sixth of the foreign born total.